Joining me today to help unpack what's unfolding
across several geopolitical hot zones, bringing
his trademark uh candor and straight talk to
the conversation is author, whistleblower,
former assistant to the CIA deputy director, John
Kiryaku. Welcome back, John. Thank you so much,
Suzy. It's good to see you. Same here. John,
I wanted to get right into things because a
lot of things are happening at the same
time at different parts of the globe. So
let's start off with Venezuela. Following the
capture of Maduro, Trump has openly floated
the what do you say the the possibility of US
intervention in all these other um jurisdictions,
Cuba, Colombia, Mexico, Iran, and most
importantly um Greenland. In that context,
I mean I feel that we're witnessing a historic
pivot in how diplomacy and foreign policy
Jon are conducted. one that no longer um fits
Realpolitik or any established school of thought,
but instead reflects a blunt might is right
logic and the open return of a colonial empire.
I I couldn't agree with you more. Um boy, there
are so many different facets to this to this
issue. I'm hearing a lot in Washington, well, it
was about the oil. It's all about the oil. It's
always about the oil. I don't think this is about
the oil. I think that and well, you know what? Let
me tell you why I don't think it's about the oil.
Because Venezuela has some of the dirtiest oil in
the world. It's it's very heavy. It's the highest
sulfur content of any oil in the world. And so
it has to be it has to be injected with with
chemicals in order to make it viable. And it
most of it can't be used for gasoline. You have to
use it for home heating oil because it's so heavy.
Uh for many many years, for decades, the only
place where Venezuela could refine that oil was
in Texas. Because in Houston, we have specialized
refineries that can handle high sulfur content
oil. It's similar to the oil in northwestern
Canada. We don't really need that oil. We're
sitting on an ocean of oil uh in in terms of um
shale oil, fracking oil here in the United States,
an ocean of it. We don't need it. It was more
about the dollar than about the oil. In 2019 2018,
Kuwait sold a shipment of oil to China and they
took payment in Yuan. This was the very first
time that a major oil deal was brokered, not using
the dollar. The United States recognized that as a
long-term threat to the American economy. And so
what better way to ensure that the petro-dollar
continues to be the currency used in international
oil transactions than to overthrow the government
that was leading the charge to use the Yuan, to
use a basket of currencies, to use the Euro or to
promote the creation of a unified bricks currency.
So I think this was more about the dollar. Now
Nicholas Maduro, I don't believe for one minute
that Nicholas Maduro was running a terrorist
state. I don't believe for a minute that Nicholas
Maduro was a "narco terrorist". If you want to
really hit narotism, attack Mexico. That's where
the cartels are. It's it's the Mexican cartels
working with the Chinese to flood the United
States with fentinyl, for example. It's not uh
Venezuela. I read something in the Washington
Post just yesterday or the day before accusing
Venezuela of being a base for Hezbollah and the
Iranian government. Well, you know what? I wrote
an article about that for the for the Los Angeles
Times. Do you know what that base is? It's a
bicycle factory. Yeah, it's a bicycle factory. But
then the argument today is, well, they could turn
that into a factory for tanks if they wanted to.
Yeah, but they haven't. And the Iranians have been
there for 20 years. So what now? Today, you're
going to decide that this is somehow a threat to
the United States, that there's a bicycle factory
in Venezuela. So really, I think that Maduro was
easy to overthrow. Um, I think that um that this
this kidnapping of Maduro has sent shock waves
uh all around the world. I think that the US
calculated correctly that the Chinese wouldn't say
anything, that the Russians wouldn't say anything,
that the Indians wouldn't say anything. And at the
same time, we just cut off Cuba's sole source
of oil. And I wouldn't be surprised now if Cuba
falls in the next 6 months. This is something
that the United States has sought for the last
65 years. So I think there are a lot of aspects
to this. Now you raised Greenland, too. I have
um I have a friend uh in the White House with whom
I had coffee yesterday and I said, "Come on, man.
What is this with Greenland? We look like fools."
And he said, "They're serious about Greenland.
They're not going to attack it, but they certainly
want to buy it". I said, "But the the king of
Denmark and the prime minister of Denmark have
both said that Greenland is not for sale." And
he said, "Well, look at it this way." He said,
"What the U.S. position is going to be in the
coming months is that the treaty that we signed
with Denmark in whenever it was 1951 or 1953,
giving us essentially unfettered rights to have
bases in Greenland and, you know, take uh rare
earth metals from Greenland, whatever. We're going
to rely on that with the argument that Greenland
is de-facto ours anyway. So just take this money
for it and we're going to keep it". I said, "Well,
that's a violation of international law." And I
said, "One of the things I think the the White
House is underestimating is the unity of the
European Union on this issue. Just day before
yesterday, every member country in the European
Union signed a document pledging support for
Denmark. I think that if the United States were
to either forcibly take Greenland or to coerce
Denmark into giving up Greenland, it would be
the end of NATO. And what would what we would
see in NATO's place would be a unified military
of the European Union, which is what they're
striving to do through the SAFE u uh doctrine.
That's exactly right. Already it's already
um started being implemented. Very interesting.
Very interesting the information you just shared.